<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Just and legal exceptions against the late act For preventing multiplicity of buldings erected within the suburbs of the City of London, and ten miles thereof, since March 1620.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46376</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829141</idno>
  <idno type="VID">33577</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248496415</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829141</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99829141e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46376)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33577)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1869:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Just and legal exceptions against the late act For preventing multiplicity of buldings erected within the suburbs of the City of London, and ten miles thereof, since March 1620.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Goldsmiths' Library, University of London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Corporation of London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Building --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33577:1"/>
            <head>Just and Legal EXCEPTIONS Against the late ACT. FOR Preventing Multiplicity of <hi>Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> Erected within the Suburbs of the City of LONDON, and ten miles thereof, since <hi>March</hi> 1620.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat this Act was made, and passed without sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of the persons concerned in it, to hear their just exceptions against its passing, contrary to the Rules of Justice, and proceedings of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Parliaments, as wil appear by Clauses 28 <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> 3. <hi>Doss.</hi> and other Records.</p>
            <p>That the Title and real scope of this Act, is directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to the Letter and Pretences in it, being onely to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, license, and encrease the multiplicity of new build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings within the Precincts aforesaid, to raise a present sum of money thereby, under a pretext of restraining and reforming them according to Law and Justice.</p>
            <p>That the Prologue of this Act declares the excessive num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of Buildings, Out-houses, and Cottages, erected and new built within the suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> and ten miles thereof, since <hi>March</hi> 1620. to be very mischievous and inconvenient, and a great Annoyance and Nuzance to the Common-wealth, and that by the Law the said Houses and Nuzances ought to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, and their Builders, Occupiers, and Tenants ought to make fines for the same, which if true, then the Parliament in justice ought not to continue and ratifie them to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33577:2"/> publike prejudice only for a present fine, and any future Parliament may abate them and fine their owners, occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and tenants notwithstanding these present fines; and this Act which cannot make them in Law to be no Nuzance, since it oft resolves and declares them such, nor restrains succeeding times from punishing them as Nuzances, if they be really such in point of Law.</p>
            <p>That these buidings in truth are no Nuzances at all by the common Law of <hi>England,</hi> for ought appears by any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Records or Law Books; but the Laws, as appears by the Book-Cases, cited in the Margent, reputes it an <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> 17 <hi>H</hi> 3 <hi>Fitz. Dower</hi> 192. <hi>Brooke Dower</hi> 18. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins Instit.</hi> 328. 29.</note> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement and benefit to the Common-Wealth, to erect houses where needful for habitation or trade, through the encrease of People; And <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cookes Instit. Fol</hi> 5. 3, <hi>Staham Fitz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rooke Ashe.</hi> Titles waste. Was it ever thought, that there could be laid four A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of land to every house to be built in Buroughs mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Towns, or to every house on the side of a navigable River built for the use of those that are not Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h skill therein.</note> waste and distruction to abate or suffer them to decay when built, for which trebble damages and the soile are forfeited by sundry Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament <hi>(viz.)</hi> 52. <hi>H.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 23. 7. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 18. 19. Which last Acts encourage buildings in or neer the precincts of Cityes and Market Towns, and declare their decay to be a great Nuzance, prejudice, and impoverish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them; neither is there any ancient Law or Statute that prohibits the erection of Houses or Cottages either in or out of Cityes, before the Statute of the 31. <hi>Eliz Cap.</hi> 7. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Cottages, (which was introductive of a new, not declarative of an old Law) extending only to Cottages and mean houses, for the habitation of mean and poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; not fair and beautiful houses of good value, for noble men, Gentlemen, Merchants, and Tradesmen of quality, were intended within that Act; therefore being no Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances at the Common Law, nor Cottages within the words or intent of the 31. <hi>Eliz. Cap.</hi> 7. it is conceived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just to declare them Nuzances, and to impose such fines upon the owners and tenants of them by this new Act.</p>
            <p>That the building and enlarging of Cityes, and their Suburbs, and of houses in them is reputed an honour, blessing, beneficial by God himself and sacred Scriptures; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut.</hi> 8. 12. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 1. <hi>Isa.</hi> 65. 21. <hi>Chap.</hi> 44. 26. 28. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15. 22. 23. 2 <hi>Chron▪</hi> 8. 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. 67. <hi>Chap..</hi> 17. 12. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26. 6. <hi>Cahp.</hi> 27. 4.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33577:2"/>
            <p> Therefore it can be no Nusance nor Greivance in Law.</p>
            <p>The first inhibition against new buildings within the City <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> and against buildings with Timber was only by King <hi>James</hi> proclaimation, by reason of the <note place="margin">A. 33.</note> great plagues in the beginning of his reign, in and about <hi>London,</hi> (to wit) by his Proclamations of the 16. <hi>April. Anno</hi> 1. 1. <hi>March. Anno.</hi> 2. 22. of <hi>October Anno</hi> 5. and the 25. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 6. <hi>Iacob,</hi> not by any Act of Parliament; which proclamations extend only to new buildings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one or two miles, and the largest of them only to three miles from the Gates of <hi>London,</hi> and no further▪ and to buidlings as well within the City, as without it in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs; and buildings which were not within that distance of two or three miles at the most from the Gates of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> were quite out of all his Proclamations; and if ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal or Nuzances were pardoned by the general pardons which he granted in the Parliament of the 3. <hi>Iacobi Cap.</hi> 27. 7. <hi>Iacobi Cap.</hi> 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. <hi>Iacobi Cap.</hi> 34. And the raising of monyes within those proclamations by King <hi>Iames</hi> though in moderate proportions, and for the most part for the poor of the Parishes wherein they were built, not for his own treasury, was murmured at and complained of as greivance: Therefore the extending of this new Act to raise moneys seaven miles beyond any of his proclamations, to all new buildings within ten miles of <hi>London,</hi> without any former Act of Parliament that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained them, must necessarily be imputed a greater greivance, and oppression of the subjects by this new Act, then any of his proclamations and proseedings upon them by his Commissioners, and a dangerous president to posterity.</p>
            <p>This Act hath a retorspect to all new buildings within the Suburbs and ten miles of <hi>London,</hi> erected since the 25. of <hi>March,</hi> 1620. till the passing of the Act 1656. Compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> full 36. years, taking in part of King <hi>James</hi> his reign, all King <hi>Charls</hi> his time, and two or three revolutions of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment since▪ Now some of these new Buildings three miles distant from <hi>London,</hi> are within the general pardon of 21 <hi>Iac</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33577:3"/> Cap. 34. and other Pardons since; others of them (within three miles) paid Fines and Compositions to King <hi>Iames</hi> and King <hi>Charles;</hi> others of them have been long since sold, and made over for full and valuable considerations, by their first Builders, and their assigns, to the present owners &amp; occupiers, who are faultlesse, and have no remedy at all to recover the fines they now pay for them, (in law or equity) against the first Builders, their Heirs, Executors, or Administrators; and yet by this Act they must be forced to pay a full years Rack-Rent for a Fine, (without any abatement) and are put in the self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same condition with those owners building on new Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within one year or month before this Act, and punished as far forth as they, (without any distinction) which they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive to be very unjust, unreasonable, and illegal; this very new Act exempting those Purchasors who have bought any Houses (built within this precinct of time) from the State, from any Fine at all; therefore by the self-same Equity, they ought to exempt all other Purchasors upon valuable conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations from others, who built them many years past, from any Fines, as well as they.</p>
            <p>The Statutes of 7 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. 31 <hi>Eliz. Cap.</hi> 5. and 21 <hi>Jac.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. Specially enact and provide for the ease of the Subjects, That all Indictments, Informations, and Actions popular, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on penal Laws, by Suit, Bill, or Information, shall be prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King and his Officers within two years space, and by Informers within one year next after the offences or forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had, made or committed against any Act or Acts, Statute, or Statutes penal, and not after the said two yeares, or one year; Which Statutes we humbly conceive to extend to all New Buildings, (admit them within the Statute of 31 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 7.) erected above two years before this late Act. 1656. and that by the Resolution of this Act it self, which provides, That no Action shall be brought against any person for any offence against it, unless it be within one year after the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed; and that by the provision of all these Statutes still in force, we ought not to be indicted, informed against, or put to fines for any new Buildings erected before the year 1654. much lefs before 1640. or King <hi>Charles</hi> his death, who should have had the Fines and Penalties, if indicted, informed,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33577:3"/> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prosecuted within two years of their first erection, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to these Acts.</p>
            <p>This new Act extends the Statute of 31 <hi>Eliz. Chap.</hi> 7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> which is against Cottages onely, to fair dwelling-Houses, which are no Cottages, within the words or meaning of it; and to Houses and Cottages within the suburbs of <hi>London, West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> and <hi>Southwark,</hi> which are ancient Cities and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs; and to Houses and Cottages near the <hi>Thames,</hi> for men of Manual Occupation, for the making, furnishing, and victualling of Ships and other Vessels used at sea, which are by express words excepted out of it; and therefore no Fines or Penalties ought to be imposed for any such Houses by this new (or any ancienter) Act.</p>
            <p>This Act impowereth the Protector to nominate and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point all Commissioners &amp; other Officers who are to execute <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> it, and impose the Fines &amp; Penalties inflicted on the owners &amp; occupiers of new Buildings, Out of every pound whereof, the Commissioners (who impose them) are to receive 3 <hi>d.</hi> in the pound for their salary and pains, and all other Officers their proportions, who being thus made Judges and Jurors in their own Cases, against all Rules of Law and Justice, encrease and exact what unreasonable Fines they please, without reason, against which there is no appeal nor remedy provided for any who are injured, which is a most sad and heavy Grievance.</p>
            <p>This Act authorizeth many particular persons within the Suburbs and ten miles off <hi>London,</hi> to build Houses for some <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> years yet to come, (paying one years full Rent and Value of them for a Fine, yet restrains all others from future building upon the like terms, undergrievous penalties, vvhich partiality vve humbly conceive to be both illegal and injurious.</p>
            <p>This Act extends not at all to any new buildings erected, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> or to be erected within the City of <hi>London</hi> it self, nor to any such buildings set up within, or near any Cities, Towns, or places through <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>York, Lincoln, Plymouth, Bristol; Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c.</hi> where many such Buildings have of late years been erected; but onely to Buildings within the Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> and ten miles thereof: Now that all Owners of Lands, and Builders, Occupiers and Tenants of new built Houses within this Precinct alone, should be thus restrained, deprived of that common Hereditary Birth-right, Liberty, Franchise, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33577:4"/> advantage of improving their Lands and Estates by new buildings within these limits, which all other their fellow-subjects and Free-men, both within <hi>London</hi> it self, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Corporations, places, and Counties of <hi>England, Wales, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> freely enjoy, without any restriction, fines, or penalties, and should be subject to so heavy, excessive Fines, Penalties, Prosecutions, Distresses, Imprisonments, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially as this Act imposeth on them, against the Common-Law, Great Charter, and common priviledge of all English Free-men, having neither forfeited these their Birth-rights by any Delinquency, and contributing equally with all others, to all publike Charges, Taxes; and suffering as much as any by the late Wars, and contributing as largely as any others, to the publike defence, in late times of greatest danger, (answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Estates;) and why they, and they alone should be thus grieved &amp; oppressed, &amp; made examples to posterity by this new Act, (to the ruine of many Widows, Orphans, and others) they can yet discern neither law, conscience, reason, or Justice: &amp; therefore humbly pray both a speedy &amp; plenary relief against <note place="margin">Let the world take notice of your Power and Justice.</note> it, and restitution of the Fines already extorted from them, and remission of those which are yet unsatisfied.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <head>31 Eliz. Chap. the 7th.</head>
            <p>FOr the avoiding of the great inconveniences which are found by experience to grow by the erecting and building of great number and multitude of Cottages, which are daily more <note place="margin">
                  <hi>There is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Statute in force against Building, but onely this of the</hi> 31 <hi>of <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </hi> 62. 7. <hi>until this new Act in</hi> 1656,</note> and more encreased in many parts of this Realme: Be it ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Queens most excellent Majesty, &amp; the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament assembled, and by the Authority of the same, That after the end of this Sessions of Parliament, no person shall within the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> make, build, or erect, or cause to be made, builded, or erected, any manner of Cottage for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation or dwelling, nor convert or ordain any building or hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, made, or hereafter to be made, to be used as a Cottage for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation or dwelling, unless the same person do assign and lay to the same Cottage or Building, four Acrres of ground at the least, to be accompted according to the Statute or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <hi>de terris mesurandis,</hi> being his or her own frée hold and inheritance, lying near to the said Cottage, to be continually
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33577:4"/> occupied and manured therewith, so long as the same Cottage shall be inhabited, upon pain that every such offendor shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit to our soveraign Lady the Quéens Majesty, her heir &amp; suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, x. li. of lawful money of <hi>England,</hi> for every such offence.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That every person which after the end of this Session of Parliament, shall willingly uphold, maintain, and continue any such Cottage hereafter to be erected, converted, or ordained for habitation or dwelling, whereunto sour acres of ground (as is aforesaid) shall not be assigned &amp; laid to be used &amp; occupied with the same, shall forfeit to our said Soveraign Lady the Queens Majesty, her heirs &amp; successors, 40. s. for every month that any such Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage shal be by him or them upholden, maintained &amp; continued. <note place="margin">☜</note>
            </p>
            <p>Provided also, &amp; be it enacted, that from, &amp; after the Feast of All-saints next comnig, there shall not be any Inmate, or more families or housholds then one, dwelling or inhabiting in any one Cottage, made, or to be made or erected, upon pain y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> every ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or occupier of any such Cottage, placing, or willingly suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any such Inmate, or other family then one, shall forfeit &amp; lose to the Lord of the Leet, within which such Cottage shall be, the sum of ten shillings of lawful money of <hi>England</hi> for every month that any such Inmate, or other family then one y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> shall dwell or inhabit in any one Cottage as aforesaid. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> all &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Lord and Lords of Leet &amp; Leets, &amp; their Stewards within the precinct of his &amp; their Leet &amp; Leecs, shall have full power &amp; authority within their several Léetes, to enquire &amp; to take pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment by the oath of Iurors, of all &amp; every offence &amp; offences in this behalf; &amp; upon such presentment had or made, to levy by distress to the use of the Lord of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Léet, all such sums of mony as so shall be forfeited: And moreover, that it shall be lawful for the Lord of every such Leet where such presentment shall be made, to recover to his own use any such forfeiture by action of debt in any of the Quéens Majesties Courts of Record, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no essoin, protection, or wager of law shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the Authority atoresaid, That all Iustices of Assises, and Iustices of Peace in all their open sessions, and everie Lord within the precinct of his Leete, and none others, shall have full power and authoritie within their severall limits and Iurisdictions, to enquire of, hear &amp; determin all offences contrary to this present Act, as well by Indictment
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33577:5"/> as otherwise by presentment or information, and to award exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for the levying of the several forfeitures aforesaid, by <hi>Fieri facias, Elegit, Capias,</hi> or otherwise as the cause shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, that this Statute or any thing therein <note place="margin">☞ <hi>Note the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of this new Act, <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> is except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but <hi>VVest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark, Brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Croyden, Bramly, Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Cities, Boroughs, and Market-towns within ten miles of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> they must pay.</hi>
               </note> contained, shall not in any wise be extended to any Cottage which shall be erected to, or for habitation or dwelling in any City, Town corporate, or ancient Borough, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Town within this Realm, nor to any Cottages or buildings which shall be erected, or converted to, and for the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary &amp; convenient habitation or dwelling of any workmen, or labourers in any mineral works, cole-mines, quarries, or delfes of stone, or slate, or in or about the making of brick, tile, lime, or coles within this Realme: So as the same Cottages or build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings be not above one mile dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant from the place of the same Mineral or other works, &amp; shall be used onely for the habitation &amp; dwelling of the said workman, nor shall in any sort prejudice, charge or impeach any person or persons, for the erecting, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, or continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of any such Cottages as are before in this proviso mention ed and specified,</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes that this Act shall not extend to any Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage <note place="margin">☞</note> to be made within a mile of the Sea, or upon the side of such part of any Navigable River where the Admirall ought to have jurisdiction, so long as no other person shall therein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit, but a Sayler or man of manuall occupation, to or for making, furnishing, or victualling of any ship or vessell, used to serve on the Sea, nor to any Cottage to be made in any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, Chase, Warren or Park, so long as no other person shall therein inhabit, but an Vnderkéeper or Warrener, for the good kéeping of the Déer, or other game of Warren, nor to any Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage heretofore made, so long as no other person shall therein inhabit, but a common Heardman, or Shepherd, for kéeping the cattel or sheep of the Town, or a poor, lame, sick, aged, or impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent person, nor to any Cottage to be made, which for any just respect upon complaint to the Iustice of Assise at the Assizes, or to the Iustices of Peace at the quarter Sessions; shall by their order entered in open Assizes or quarter Sessions, be decréed to continue for habitation, for, and during so long time onely, as by such Decrée shall be tollerated and limited.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>